<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Did you say data?</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Did you say data?</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Terrorism Analysis</title>
      <link>/project/global-terrorism-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/global-terrorism-analysis/</guid>
      <description> Overview  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cancer Classification via Gene Expression</title>
      <link>/project/cancer-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/cancer-classification/</guid>
      <description>Overview Cancer classification is one of the vital areas of medical sciences. In this project, we examine the Gene Expression data for various types of cancer and classify each cancer into its subtypes. We gather the samples from GEO datasets and select the best features using the class-overlap score, standard deviation by mean ratio, ANOVA – F value and $\chi^2$ (Chi-square) statistics. We then run the following classifiers: K Nearest Neighbors, Naïve Bayes and Decision Trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter Engine</title>
      <link>/project/twitter-engine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/twitter-engine/</guid>
      <description>Overview The application can be seen at https://github.com/krohitm/Twitter-Simulator.
In this project, we implemented a Twitter Clone and a client tester/simulator.
As part I of this project, we built an engine that (in part II) will be paired up with WebSockets to provide full functionality. Specific things done in this project are:
 Implemented a Twitter like engine with the following functionality:   Register account. Send tweet. Tweets can have hashtags and mentions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter Simulator</title>
      <link>/project/twitter-simulator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/twitter-simulator/</guid>
      <description>Overview Link to demo video: https://youtu.be/XlY2eoI5o-8
Part I of this project can be seen at https://github.com/krohitm/Twitter-Simulator
The part I of our project had all the functionalities working. In part II, we have used Phoenix web framework to implement a WebSocket interface to our part I implementation. This implementation was achieved by fulfilling the following tasks:
 Designed a JSON based API that represents all messages and their replies (including errors).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>